{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man liberated Bulgaria from 400 years of Ottoman rule following a successful siege of Pleven. He employed Dmitri Milyutin to open army recruitment to all social classes, and he encouraged the new zemstvo system of local government. Loris-Melikov’s work with this leader to establish a parliament was thwarted when this leader was assassinated by the People’s Will in St. Petersburg. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who emancipated the serfs.",
      "answer": "Alexander II"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kelcy Warren serves as the CEO sponsoring this project, which was prohibited from utilizing space under Lake Oahe by the Army Corps of Engineers in December 2016. Shailene Woodley was arrested while protesting this project, which Energy Transfer Partners intends to run to Illinois from the Bakken fields. For ten points, name this pipeline that, controversially, is to run through the Standing Rock Indian Reservation.",
      "answer": [
        "Dakota Access Pipeline or DAPL",
        "Bakken Pipeline before Bakken is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist is often credited with inventing the anchor escapement used in pendulum clocks. Isaac Newton’s quote “If I have seen further it is by standing on the shoulder of giants” was probably a jab at this scientist’s short height. He wrote about his use of microscopes in his book Micrographia, and his namesake law can be stated as restoring force is proportional to displacement. For ten points, name this British scientist who coined the term “cell.”",
      "answer": "Robert Hooke"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. A group advocating this action modeled its activities on the Bryce Group in Britain. Edward House drafted a plan calling for this action, which relied upon the work of the Phillimore Committee. William Borah and Henry Cabot Lodge opposed this action, citing their disapproval of Article Ten of a certain proposed covenant. For ten points, name this action, never taken despite the efforts of President Woodrow Wilson, which doomed a certain international body to irrelevance.",
      "answer": [
        "the United States joining the League of Nations",
        "equivalent descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s father launched the 1970 Corrective Revolution. A revolution against this leader began after a boy was arrested for political graffiti in Daraa. To stop the Southern Front and Army of Conquest, this Ba’athist leader allegedly ordered his air force to use barrel bombs in an ongoing civil war. This leader brokered a ceasefire with Vladimir Putin shortly after recapturing Aleppo in December 2016. For ten points, name the current president of Syria.",
      "answer": "Bashar al-Assad"
    },
    {
      "question": "One man accomplished this feat after the widow of Zarephath accused him of bringing her sins to remembrance. Before accomplishing this feat, another man uttered “Talitha kum;” he was delayed from performing this action by a continuously bleeding woman. On a different occasion, after waiting two extra days to perform this action, the same man’s emotional response is recorded in the shortest verse in the Bible. The phrase “Jesus wept” occurs immediately before an instance of, for ten points, what miracle that Jesus performed for Lazarus?",
      "answer": [
        "raising the dead",
        "descriptions of Elijah and/or Jesus resurrecting someone",
        "raising the son of the widow of Zarephath and/or the daughter of Jairus and/or Lazarus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was deposed after losing at Flarchheim to Rudolph of Swabia. As a child, this man was targeted in the Kaiserswerth plot that left Anno II as regent. This man prompted a conflict by installing Guibert of Ravenna as Antipope Clement III. This man walked to Canossa Castle barefoot to beg forgiveness from Gregory VII after a dispute involving the pope’s authority to appoint bishops. For ten points, name this Holy Roman Emperor embroiled in the Lay Investiture controversy.",
      "answer": "Henry IV, Holy Roman Emperor or Heinrich IV"
    },
    {
      "question": "The technology of square set timbering was developed to aid in the extraction of this commodity. Investors who held stockpiles of this commodity nicknamed a piece of harmful legislation the “Crime of ‘73.” John Sherman names an act that required the U.S. government to purchase this commodity. The Bland-Allison Act mandated that the government create coins from, for ten points, what metal, which was once traded at a sixteen to one ratio for gold?",
      "answer": "silver"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Negroli family, based in Milan, was a key producer of these objects. These objects were manufactured in Greenwich for English monarchs. Decorated versions of these objects were worn at tilts, and Japanese objects of this type were made from overlapping leather scales. These objects included the hauberk and gauntlets, and Roman legionaries wore types of these made from mail or plates. For ten points, name these protective outfits that were used in jousting and medieval warfare.",
      "answer": [
        "suits of armor",
        "any specific piece of armor, such as hauberks",
        "gauntlets before they are mentioned, helmets, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, one side was saved by timely naval support from the Lexington and Tyler. Nathan Bedford Forrest led a charge along the Corinth Road in this battle, which turned with the arrival of Don Buell’s Army of the Ohio. Albert Sidney Johnston was killed early in this battle as his troops attacked the Hornet’s Nest in an attempt to push Union forces away from Pittsburgh Landing. For ten points, name this 1862 victory in Tennessee for Ulysses S. Grant.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Shiloh",
        "Battle of Pittsburg Landing before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man gained power by exiling the chancellor William Longchamp. He gained the territories of Brittany and Normandy after the Treaty of Le Goulet with Philip II Augustus, but lost them after his defeat at the Battle of Bouvines. After this man tried to appoint an Archbishop of Canterbury, Innocent III excommunicated him. For ten points, name this brother of Richard the Lionheart who, after being confronted by English nobles at Runnymede, signed the Magna Carta.",
        "answer": [
          "King John",
          "John Lackland",
          "John I"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John’s tyranny, culminating in the breach of the Magna Carta just a few months after its signing, led nobles of this rank to revolt in a namesake war.",
        "answer": [
          "barons",
          "the First Barons’ War"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s self-described “oldest neighborhood” of Corktown contains its abandoned eighteen-story Central Station. The Ambassador Bridge spans this city’s namesake river, connecting it to Windsor. A riot centered on this city’s 12th Street was quelled when George Romney called in the National Guard in summer 1967. The Renaissance Center, home to GM, was built near the Chrysler Freeway in, for ten points, what Michigan city, home to America’s “Big Three” automakers?",
        "answer": "Detroit"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the 1967 riot, the National Guard initially limited itself to patrolling this road, which marks the northern border of Detroit. Its name is synonymous with the segregation between the heavily- black city itself and its whiter, more affluent suburbs.",
        "answer": "Eight Mile Road"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismandecidednottocontestanelectionafterEstesKefauverwontheNewHampshireprimary.This man used Turnip Day as an opportunity to attack the Republican majorities in the 80th Congress. This man, who ordered the integration of the armed forces, suffered in popularity later for his nationalization of the steel mills during the Korean War. For ten points, name this president who was not defeated by Dewey during the 1948 Presidential election.",
        "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1948, Truman’s Secretary of State introduced this economic policy, which sent a large amount of aid to help rebuild the economies of Western Europe.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshall Plan or the European Recovery Program",
          "ERP",
          "George Marshall"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest surviving example of this instrument is named after King Charles IX of France, who commissioned it in 1560. A difficult sonata for this instrument by Giuseppe Tartini is nicknamed “Devil’s Trill.” J.S. Bach wrote a set of sonatas and partitas as solos for this instrument, which was made in Cremona by families like Guarneri and Amati. For ten points, name this highest-pitched string instrument to be manufactured by Antonio Stradivari.",
        "answer": "violin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This violin virtuoso, who legendarily sold his soul to the devil, composed a set of twenty-four Caprices for solo violin.",
        "answer": "Niccolo Paganini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While defending this government, Jaroslaw Dombrowski supposedly asked “do they still think me a traitor?” as he died. Gustave Courbet fled to Switzerland after advocating the destruction of the Vendˆome Column during this government’s tenure. Supporters of this government were shot at the Federalists’ Wall in P`ere Lachaise [pair la-shez] during the Bloody Week, in which Marshal MacMahon restored control for Adolphe Thiers [tee-air]. For ten points, name this revolutionary socialist government, formed after the Franco-Prussian War in the French capital.",
        "answer": "Paris Commune"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adolphe Theirs was the first president of this French government, which lasted until France’s defeat in World War II.",
        "answer": "French Third Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer’s opposition to the collection of indemnities by William Ament after the Boxer Rebellion prompted him to write an essay “To the Person Sitting in Darkness.” This author made a chronicle of a westward stagecoach journey with his brother Orion. This author of Roughing It also wrote about his early years as an apprentice to a steamboat captain in Life on the Mississippi, in which he explained the genesis of his pen name. For ten points, name this author, born Samuel Langhorne Clemens, famous for his Adventures of Tom Sawyer.",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens before read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An 1873 book by Mark Twain and Charley Dudley Warner lends its title to what time period in American history between 1870 and 1900, in which post-Civil War opulence hid the unsavory nature of urban poverty?",
        "answer": [
          "the Gilded Age",
          "Gilded Age: A Tale of Today"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man tried to force Richard Corbin to pay for gunpowder that had been seized by Lord Dunmore. Thanks to a speech noting that “Caesar had his Brutus; Charles I his Cromwell,” this man was accused of treason towards George III. In another speech, this man asked “is life so dear, or peace so sweet, as to be purchased at the price of chains and liberty?” For ten points, name this Virginian Founding Father who declared “Give me liberty or give me death!”",
        "answer": "Patrick Henry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Patrick Henry’s treasonous speech was given within his first two weeks as a member of this Virginian legislative body.",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was threatened by a rival expedition led by Francisco de Garay. He invaded Honduras to defeat his rebellious lieutenant Crist´obal the Old. This man was attacked by his rivals Diego Velazquez and Bishop Fonseca in the Council of the Indies. This man burned his ships after landing at modern Veracruz and allied with the people of Tlaxcala [t’lahsh-kah-lah]. He captured Montezuma II in his capital of Tenochtitlan and created the Viceroyalty of New Spain. For ten points, name this conquistador who conquered the Aztec Empire.",
        "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cortes implemented this system of forced labor in New Spain, where a number of natives were granted to conquistadors, who in return were supposed to protect them and convert them.",
        "answer": "encomienda"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "U.S. States Before They Were States",
      "prompt": "Which modern U.S. state was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Russian territory and now has capital Juneau?",
          "answer": "Alaska"
        },
        {
          "question": "Known as “Indian Territory,” north of Texas?",
          "answer": "Oklahoma"
        },
        {
          "question": "A kingdom ruled by the House of Kamehameha? [ka-may-ha-may-ha]",
          "answer": "Hawaii"
        },
        {
          "question": "A debtor’s colony founded by James Oglethorpe?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of the Bear Flag Revolt?",
          "answer": "California"
        },
        {
          "question": "The eventual home of the unrecognized state of Franklin?",
          "answer": "Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of the 1794 Battle of Fallen Timbers in the Northwest Territory?",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of the 1819 Saginaw Cession?",
          "answer": "Michigan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Protestantism in France",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "”Reformed” group of Calvinists that fought with the French crown during the Wars of Religion and were protected by the Edict of Nantes [nahnt].",
          "answer": "Huguenots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city that the Protestant Henry IV declared was “well worth a mass” on converting to Catholicism.",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Sun King” who revoked the Edict of Nantes in 1685.",
          "answer": "Louis XIV"
        },
        {
          "question": "1572 massacre of French Protestants ordered by the Queen Mother, Catherine d’Medici.",
          "answer": "St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that supported the Protestants through its cadet House of Cond´e. It was the last royal house of France.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cardinal who fought French Protestants while serving Louis XIII.",
          "answer": "Richelieu"
        },
        {
          "question": "1685 edict that revoked the Edict of Nantes.",
          "answer": "Edict of Fontainebleau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that was a haven for French Protestants until its destruction by Louis XIII. It was reinforced by the English Duke of Buckingham.",
          "answer": "La Rochelle"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Genocide",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Genocide carried out by Nazi Germany against “undesirable” people.",
          "answer": "Holocaust or Shoah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish concentration camp, which included an extermination camp at Birkenau, used during that genocide.",
          "answer": "Auschwitz-Birkenau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dutch city where the International Criminal Court prosecutes perpetrators of genocide.",
          "answer": "The Hague"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group targeted by an Ottoman genocide during World War I, now denied by the Turkish government.",
          "answer": "Armenian people"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern country that was the site of the Holodomor famine and is the site of Russian military intervention.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western region of Sudan, subject to fighting between the government and Janjaweed militias.",
          "answer": "Darfur genocide"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sudanese President indicted by the ICC for that genocide.",
          "answer": "Omar al-Bashir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where colonial Germans committed a genocide of the Herero and Namaqua people.",
          "answer": "Namibia"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s exile to Europe was reported by Lauren Lyman. His expedition to aid China after a flood is documented by the book North to the Orient. This man, who proposed a neutrality pact with Germany and supported the (20 pts)",
        "America First movement, had his son kidnapped by Bruno Hauptmann in the “Crime of the Century.” In 1927, this man won the Orteig Prize for his (10 pts)",
        "journey from Roosevelt Field to Le Bourget Field. For ten points, name this American aviator who undertook the first non-stop trans-Atlantic flight."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Just before leaving for this event, Jed Bartlett teaches the Secretary of Agriculture how to pick a Chief of Staff in a Season One episode of The West Wing titled “He Shall, from Time to Time...”. That episode title references Article (20 pts)",
        "2, Section 3 of the Constitution, detailing the need for these events. Kiefer Sutherland’s character becomes President because he is the (10 pts)",
        "“designated survivor” of this event in a 2016 ABC drama. For ten points, name this annual political speech given by the President to a joint session of Congress."
      ],
      "answer": "State of the Union address or speech, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A legend about this battle notes that the losing king was saved by an angel who turned him to marble. The Hungarian Orban designed the Basilica and Dardanelles guns for use in this battle in an attempt to breach the (20 pts)",
        "Theodosian Walls. The winning side in this battle used a series of greased logs to transport ships across the Golden Horn. (10 pts)",
        "Mehmed II was victorious in, for ten points, what 1453 siege in which the Ottomans captured the capital of the Byzantine Empire, renaming it Istanbul?"
      ],
      "answer": "1453 Siege or Battle, etc. of Constantinople"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was harshly criticized by the EU after the appointees to its Constitutional Tribunal were abruptly changed by the newly-elected Law and Justice Party in 2015. The perpetrator of the 2016 Berlin Christmas Market attack (20 pts)",
        "hijacked and killed a truck driver from this country. During October 2016, thousands of women in this country participated in the “Black Monday” protests against a proposed total (10 pts)",
        "ban on abortion. For ten points, name this predominantly Catholic country led by Andrzej [andr-zhay] Duda from Warsaw."
      ],
      "answer": "Poland or Polska"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, James Dalyell’s attempt to ambush one side’s leader prompted the Battle of Bloody Run. During this conflict’s siege of Fort Pitt, Jeffrey Amherst used smallpox-infected (20 pts)",
        "blankets as a weapon. Popular myth holds that colonists were barred from settling west of the Appalachians following this conflict, which supposedly prompted George III to issue the Proclamation of (10 pts)",
        "1763. For ten points, name this revolt of native American tribes in the Great Lakes region, led by an Ottawa chief."
      ],
      "answer": "Pontiac’s Rebellion or War, Uprising, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this country packed the head of a rival in ice so that he could communicate with it. Black dogs in this country were hunted down after the disgraced Clement Barbot was thought to have transfigured; Barbot was later caught in person by the (20 pts)",
        "Tonton Macoute police. In 2011, when former president Jean-Claude Duvalier returned to this poorest country in the Western Hemisphere, he was arrested on corruption charges upon his arrival in (10 pts)",
        "Port-au-Prince. For ten points, name this nation that shares the island of Hispaniola with the Dominican Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Haiti"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This school of philosophy argued that purely incorporeal “being” did not exist and divided the world into four categories, including “substance” and “quality.” The concept of adiaphora, or actions outside the realm of morality, was (20 pts)",
        "first propounded by this school of thought. One proponent of this school of thought frequently encouraged himself to “Erase impressions!” and wrote his (10 pts)",
        "Meditations while on a military campaign. Zeno of Citium founded, for ten points, what school of Ancient Greek thought, followed by Marcus Aurelius, that stressed virtue and freedom from emotion?"
      ],
      "answer": "Stoicism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Academic Legion toppled a government in this empire when Franz von Pillersdorf failed to repeal censorship laws. This empire lost possession of Lombardy in the Treaty of Villafranca during the Italian Wars of Independence. Following (20 pts)",
        "Francis I’s defeat at Austerlitz and the ensuing Treaty of Pressburg, the Holy Roman Empire was effectively reorganized as this empire. In 1867, this empire entered into the (10 pts)",
        "Ausgleich dual-monarchy under Franz Joseph I. For ten points, name this empire that merged with Hungary in the 19th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Austrian Empire"
    }
  ]
}